all right keeping with the co-authorship
theme next talk is a 25 minute recorded
talk by Alex kefir resilience and active
inference
2024 this is Alex
kefir this is Alex kefir I'm here to
present some ideas on on resilience and
active inference um so this is largely
just a unpacking in a careful way of
some Concepts from this paper from 2022
that I was involved in um but also will
explore some some novel directions um
that this uh this thinking has taken
since
then so the concept of resilience really
if you look at the emology it's just it
means like the capacity to recoil
essentially or to or to to bounce back
or just to survive through hardship and
change um so obviously this concept is
sort of a fundamental one if you're
looking at uh life life forms um
dynamical systems more generally um in
the context of like um ecosystems and
sustainability it's an important concept
um so that's why we're interested in
this um it's actually also sort of a
fundamental Concept in Material Science
so so since this paper has come out I've
been approached a couple of times by by
journals of Material Science for um for
follow-ups and such um so as I said the
the fundamental concept has to do with
recoiling or bouncing back um but
there's sort of there are some
peripheral sort of different facets of
this of this meaning and we explored all
of these in this paper um so roughly
speaking you can think of resilience in
sort of three ways um so first there's
inertia um so inertia I mean I guess
literally just means really uh uh sort
of not changing um so persistence uh but
you can also think of it as resistance
in the sense that right unless you're
unless you're a exist in a vacuum uh
then you're a system that's embedded in
some broader system and inertia is
basically continuing on your way despite
changes uh that might that might occur
or interactions with that broader system
um so if you think of the red arrow as
representing the path of a of a
subsystem or an H through its state
space then and The Black Arrow is some
kind of potential disturbance um then
the top diagram here illustrates
inertia um the central meaning again of
resilience arguably is elasticity or the
ability to bounce back so in that case
you undergo some perturbation or change
um and you end up recovering your
initial doesn't have to be that you
recover your exact initial position but
the point is you make your way back to a
reasonable state in terms of the kind of
system that you are
um then there's also this sort of third
thing called we call plasticity or
adaptation um so in this case you begin
in one configuration uh the red arrow at
the beginning here and after the perturb
uh the perturbation or disturbance you
end up in a slightly different
configuration so that should be read not
as just that you change your state like
you update your um your beliefs in the
time scale of infers or something but
you actually you actually wind up
somewhat adjusting your model in
response to this change um so this is
more like something like Al estasis
um whereas ticity is returning to the
same state um so i' say there are some
close relationships just to to get into
some philosophical conceptual analysis
for a second here um the first thing uh
inertia probably doesn't really exist in
its pure form right in nature in a way
or
it it if it does it it reduces to sort
of elasticity so you know I mean
presumably if you if you perturb a
system um then you have to cause some
change in the system however slight um
otherwise there hasn't been a physical
interaction right uh and inertia is
going to look in practice just like the
capacity to sort of instantly recover um
from that Tiny from that tiny change um
there there is in the limit case there
is sort of of different meaning here
because again there might just not be a
change but I think um I think in the
context of realistic systems there will
always be some some interaction um but
arguably these two these two concepts
are very close um plasticity seems like
um on the face of it like a different
thing because um well first of all uh
the ability to be to be plastic in this
sense sort of explains how you could
come to have this property of elasticity
um so if you look at the example of
neuroplasticity for example um it's the
ability to adapt to change and to
basically update your your synaptic
weights to arrive at a new model that
allows you to be uh in part allows you
to be resilient in these first two
senses um but there's another sense in
which if you just assume that there's
some property of the system that doesn't
change through this um through this
process which I think is a reasonable
assumption in the case of uh you know
biological systems um then there's going
to be some kernel of the system that
survives through change and then you're
back to your sort of original definition
um okay so if we look at this concept
through the lens of the free energy
principle um I mean first of all it
turns out to be a very fundamental at
you know as is often the case when you
try to unpack um sort of uh fundamental
properties of of systems in nature in
terms of the FP and active inference uh
you find that there's a fairly direct
mapping from the properties that the FP
attributes to systems or um the types of
systems that are well described by the
FP and this uh and this concept of
resilience um so I mean Carl friston has
said in discussions of this that
essentially
uh systems well described by the fdp are
resilient um uh full stop so uh but we
can look at at the three uh facets of
the meaning of resilience here so
um certainly systems described by the Fe
are they have this property of inertia
in the sense that um by definition right
they're things that have managed to
persist so they limit their exposure to
uh to unlikely States unlikely
observations um but they're also sort of
by definition elastic systems um because
because they have this attracting set so
um having an attracting set of States
means that um you know of course there
might be changes or perturbations that
are sort of catastrophic that destroy
the system but as long as the system is
not destroyed then by definition it's
going to make it make its way back to
the subtracting set of States um so
resilience in the core sense is really a
um almost a defining feature of systems
that are described by the FP uh and then
finally plasticity you can think of as
something like basian model selection um
on some time scale and so that that
might seem like something extra but it's
only extra if the multiscale aspect of
the FP is extra and I would argue that
that it really isn't because at its
heart the FP is a is a scale-free
description of things and this
multiscale and scale free are sort of uh
sort of um connected Notions um so
that's
plasticity um okay but so most of the
interest I'd say of this lies in the the
mapping of resilience onto this this
formalism um of active inference so uh a
key concept uh in this analysis is the
notion of degeneracy and this is is a uh
somewhat technical term um here we're
follow we mainly follow on the
definition of and and in fact the
analysis of degeneracy in terms of
active inference in uh Sajid at all 2020
this is a great paper on this topic um
so here we have just the expression for
variational free energy um in the top
row um is a expression in terms of
basically a Helm hols free energy so
it's an energy term minus an entropy
term uh uh so if you just look at that
for a second
um the we've identified uh again
following this paper from 2020 we've
identified degeneracy with the entropy
term um so we'll get into why that is in
a second um but basically uh if the
concept of degeneracy is useful
redundancy um so this you can think of
this as like complexity that that earns
its keep or that's worth having um so
complexity in this this bottom breakdown
of variational free energy uh you uh you
analyze it in terms of complexity which
is a the the difference the K Divergence
between the prior belief uh Over States
the the generative density Over States
and the approximate posterior so this is
kind of like how how difficult is it or
how much change has to uh does the
system have to undergo in order to
represent the states that are um
inferred from some observations um
what's what's what's the departure
between that posterior distribution and
the prior dist distribution Over States
uh that's complexity um minus accuracy
um the the the expected uh log
probability of observations given
States um so what's the connection
between complexity and this idea of
useful redundancy uh sorry of just
redundancy um there's there's a
assumption here that complexity and
redundancy are closely related um I
think the basic idea is that so
redundancy uh in this context is quite
literally just duplication of States um
so the I'd say the classic example is
like an error correcting code so if
you're trying to transmit some uh a bit
of information over a channel uh you
might you might send 10 copies of a bit
in case in case some of those bits get
flipped or corrupted uh and you want to
make sure that the that the message gets
transmitted um so that's redundancy it
increases the complexity because um uh
well one way of looking at it is that it
uh it it it increases the description
length uh right this this K Divergence
is like how how how much how much more
do you have to say in order to
communicate that an event drawn from
this Q distribution has occurred um G
given that you assume this P
distribution um so uh so you can think
of it as well what these these extra
bits are are the Redundant bits um so
there there's a sort of conceptual
connection between complexity and
redundancy
um and then degeneracy on this first
definition is just the complexity that
serves some purpose and we'll get into
that in the moment um it's just also
important to note that there's this
definition of um degeneracy as partial
redundancy in the in the literature uh
and this is partial overlap and function
so um the idea is that um redundancy
exists in a system uh sorry degeneracy
resists uh exists to the extent that
multiple states in the system serve some
function in common but then those States
also have um otherwise uh have distinct
or disjoint sets of of functions um and
in practice I think these two almost
always line up so there might be sort of
uh limit edge cases in which um in which
they're different but in but in practice
um right if you have multiple States
they'll always have some different
properties and therefore um perform some
different functions
okay so so this is one of the core
things that we pointed out in this paper
um of ours so
um this this actually sorry this
breakdown is from the sjad all 2020
paper uh but we sort of have a different
gloss on the Central Center term here um
so this is the complexity term in the
variational free energy you can break
this down in terms of um further break
this down in terms of this uh
expectation under Q of the negative log
probability of States under the
generative model um so this is called a
cost term in the 2020 paper um we
describe this in epistemic terms as as
as an uncertainty term so this is uh
this is basically uh you can you can
read this as the Shannon uh minimum
description length of the of the states
given the generative density um but it's
sort of the expected surprise um how
surprising are are these states that I
that I infer uh using the variational
posterior under my generative model um
so that's an uncertainty term uh and
then we subtract this degeneracy or the
entropy over um over the variation of
posterior Over States um so I mean first
of all sorry I realized that I didn't
quite make the the link here between um
degeneracy and entropy so why is this
the case uh why do we identify these uh
it's it's because um
this means if if the if if this Q
distribution Over States is higher in
entropy it means that there's a um
degenerate mapping in the likelihood
from states to observations right so
meaning for multiple States uh you can
get the same
observation um and so then when you
invert that likelihood uh mapping in
order to recover this posterior um this
means that for one observation you might
have several um several different states
and the spread of the of the
distribution Over States of course is
just the entropy so that's that's the
link to to genery there uh so so this
complexity term is uncertainty minus
degeneracy um one reason that's
interesting is that when this complexity
is zero um it's not as if the system is
completely certain of what's going on um
the uncertainty term actually remains
it's just balanced by this degeneracy in
other words all of the uncertainty in
this ideal case um is
is useful um and so I think this really
this really captures what what
degeneracy in this context amounts to um
it's uncertainty that's useful and is
it's useful precisely because there's
some amount of uncertainty that's
inherent in the source of the
information you're trying to model right
so um here p is the the in this context
is the generative model that the system
has of um it's the sort of internal
generative model of of the external
States um and so there will be some
right there'll be some entropy some
Source entropy associated with that
system that that you're trying to model
and um so long as you match your
variational posterior matches that
degree of uncertainty um then you're in
sort of an optimal um an optimal model
so in other words for maximum model
goodness try to ensure that um P equals
Q um so uh this ties nicely into the
idea plasticity resilience is plasticity
so your goal here is to adjust the
posterior to match the generative model
essentially um so you can do that um you
know in in like perceptual inference uh
you can try to infer a state uh a q
distribution this is again an
approximation to the posterior the true
posterior over over those States under
the generative model um but equally you
can adjust the generative model in in a
in a multiscale setting you can learn
learn or adjust update the parameters of
the generative density in order to match
what's in the external World um
so right this this complexity term um is
affected by changes to p as well as
changes in Q and so I think the
fundamental idea that I had here was
that
um in an ideal uh sort of optimal system
under the free energy principle you
should expect um first of all P will be
adjusted so as to model the environment
for sort of um basic you know um free
energy principle SLG good regulator
theorem types of reasons uh and then Q
will also be adjusted to match to match
P um so this involves um this cybernetic
principle called The Law of requisite
variety which is sort of a um um it's
closely related to the good regul good
regulator theorem um but basically it
just says that you know if you're trying
to regulate or control some States then
you need uh at least as much uh variety
or uh in probabilistic terms that that
translates to variance um or or entropy
um you need as much Variety in the
controller as you have in the in the
environment and so it's a fairly
intuitive thing because you basically
need sufficiently many degrees of
freedom in the controller uh to be able
to map to to model what's in the
environment um so you can see this as
this degeneracy um
property of resilient systems or uh any
system under the FP as as an instance of
this law of of requisite variety it's
also clearly by the way a an obvious
case of constrained maximum entropy so
there's work um showing that many many
lines of thought really showing that the
active inference uh sorry the free
energy principle is um is equivalent to
a principle of constrained maximum
entropy uh so here the constraint is
this uh you can you can think of this as
constrained by accuracy
um but you you basically maximize this
entropy term subject to that constraint
uh subject to the generative
model okay so um looking just a bit more
closely at this notion of degeneracy um
so I've said that it's Central um one
pointed question you might ask here is
well are all do all resilient systems uh
have this degeneracy property uh and so
I want to say the answer is yes um so
the type of degeneracy that we've
already talked about is this degeneracy
and the likelihood mapping uh so this is
multiple States mapping to the same
observation um and again that's uh that
can be cast as you'd expect to see that
given um that you're performing maximum
entropy inference um so that that is um
crucial but equally important I'd say is
degeneracy and the
Dynamics uh so this characterizes just
systems that again that have an
attracting set of States so if these STS
are states at a given time and then st+
one is the state or set of States at the
next time step um so this in order for
for a system to be resilient um it
really has to be the case that this
transition um uh that these transition
probabilities or the Dynamics of the
system are such that um that that
mapping itself is degenerate um so you
know this means that basically you can
perturb the system in several different
ways and you'll still arrive uh you'll
still end up at the same at the same uh
state or or set of attracting States um
obviously if the if the perturbation is
too large then that might not be the
case the system will diverge and you'll
destroy you'll destroy it but by
definition the systems that survive
through change are the ones that have
this
property um so there is a very deep link
between resilience and genery if you
consider Dynamics as
well um just a couple more points here
one is um something that I've recently
been thinking about uh it's it's it's
actually a theme that's been on my mind
for some time but I've recently written
about it in some other work um and this
is what what does the principle of
requisite variety and um what do these
concepts of degeneracy and resilience
look like in in the context of
multiscale active inference um but
specifically here I don't I don't just
mean um the fact that excuse me the fact
that model parameters as well as states
can change but I mean U multiscale
active inference in the sense that
you've got potentially higher level
agents that are composed of lower level
agents um so in that kind of setting uh
requisite variety ends up looking like
the the property of higher level agents
that they're composed of a variety of
different types of lower level agents um
so I mean I would argue that if you
combine this law of requisite variety
with multiscale active inference in this
sense then you really sort of
automatically have something like a a
diverse ecosystem in which there are
many different types of agents that
participate um so here in this diagram
we're illustrating first of all just the
same degenerate State observation
mapping that we saw in the uh in the
previous slides um but here the nodes
are individual agents that compose this
higher level
agent
um also as pointed out in this paper
um by by um Carl friston and Daniel
fredman at all um the in this kind of
context different agents can be expected
to and I think empirically in some
simulations are shown to take on the
roles of these different types of States
so uh of course the breakdown here is in
terms of active and sensory and uh
active sensory and internal States so
here you've got active sensory and
internal agents uh and that's one I
would argue of this um application of
the of the law of requisite
variety um to this higher level uh
system um I also show here the the
policy selection based on expected free
energy for completeness um but that's
sort of the main the main point is this
this specialization and diversification
of Agents um in this in this setting um
in terms of the second definition of
degeneracy you can also think of these
agents as playing um somewhat distinct
but partially overlapping roles um and
there's some some lots of interesting
work on um on that sort of multi-agent
perspective from the point of view of
active
inference um so that's really it I'm
just going to conclude with some with
sort of a philosophical question that I
think is is kind of important for um for
tying this this together and and sort of
checking that it that it just makes
sense um so I've said earlier that um
any system well described by the FP as
res so hold on a second uh not all
systems are equally resilient though uh
right tups by are sort of the paradig of
a fragile as opposed to resilient object
so since the FP describes things in
general doesn't it mean that all things
are resilient um and doesn't that
contradict this obvious fact so I think
the answer here is that it's simply it's
a matter of scale so yes all things are
resilient all things that is things that
are reidentified over time and that
persist through change um all such
things are resilient but it's a matter
of scale so if you if you introduce a
very slight perturbation to this
teacup um very slight you know um
relative to a certain a certain
reference frame or a certain scale but
large enough right relative to the scale
on which that system is resilient then
by definition it will survive right and
so obviously again in a in a a real
universe in which there are interactions
and you're you're always interacting in
some way dealing with some sort of um
random
fluctuations um then yes for the system
to persist through time to be inert and
elastic um it has some right the
material has some uh coherence that
allows it to to persist through those
changes so it is a resilient system it's
just that if you introduce a change
that's um on a scale that's That's too
great for the system to handle then
it'll be destroyed um but sort of the
just the basic coherence as a spao
temporal object of this teacup is itself
a form of resilience uh and then we get
when we get into more complex forms of
life more complex generative models
that's when we when we when we begin to
see more um impressive forms of
resilience and shading it even into into
plasticity and the ability to to really
survive through more significant
changes so thanks for for listening SL
watching um I'm happy to participate in
this Symposium um thanks to all the
other uh the co-authors of this um paper
by Mark Mall in 2022 that was the
departure point for this work uh yeah
thank you